this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
softball digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size
they're moving infrastructure friction
and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials and an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio welcome everyone to software
engineering radio today I'll be your
host my name is Kim Carter and today
we've got this fan Lam this flim is a
cryptographer computer scientist in
entrepreneur he's the co-founder and CEO
of treszura the in doing encrypted file
sync and sharing tool in 2016
Istvan was featured on Forbes Europe's
30 under 30 and technology list is an
inspiring young leader and technology in
2017 he received a digital solution
special prize at ey Entrepreneur of the
Year awards welcome to the show -
welcome everybody thanks for inviting me
we've had shows on the texes reduction
with an Italy silvina which now that was
show number 330 and have had another
related show in twin encryption with
Peter Budaj show number 321 also from
treszura and also a disclaimer I use
Twitter at myself and have found it to
be excellent thanks thanks for it a nice
words there's a relevant article from
the I Triple E Computer Society on
today's topic the impact of the new
European journal data protection
regulation that's gdpr
on the information government stalker in
Health and Social Care with special
reference to primary care in England now
today we're going to be discussing how
to build software with
see by design in mind oh that's a GDP
our requirement so I'm just gonna start
off with some basic questions can you
explain this one what GDP are stands for
and what it is and why it came about
sure
so GDP are has been introduced in the
year in 25th of May this year so it is
in effect right now and it regulates how
European data subjects how to handle
data the data of European data subjects
and it does not stop at the border of EU
it's actually software engineers and
everybody or providers need to take care
of this regulation even outside of the
year so whenever you are handling the
data alpha knee you citizen a resident
you need to comply with this regulation
and it is actually I think a quite good
standard and it might be a potential
standard a global standard for handling
private data because if you look at for
instance in Brazil they just followed
this regulation the implement is
something quite similar to GDP are and
Mark Zuckerberg himself told a
congressional hearing that's us
should introduce something similar to
GDP our I don't know how serious he was
but but GDP are itself is sets a new way
of looking at private information and
private data and I think this regulation
can can take back to the trust in the
industry because if people private
individuals lose trust in our industry
in a software industry and the cloud and
and everything else then no data will be
transmitted to to these same systems
that means big harm for the industry
it's something like people are losing
trust in banks and not taking their
money to the banks so if this regulation
I think is is important not just because
for private individuals but it's also
from
or industry players perspective because
that can reinitiate trust with their
predator in the videos who does gdpr
effect and who is responsible for
creating and enforcing it
so enforcement is done by the local or
national authorities they the protection
authorities of the member sites meaning
28 different authorities so even even
it's a EU level regulation it's an
umbrella regulation there are still a
little bit fragmented by how's it
interpreted by difference authorizes
inside of you but at least the language
is it is the same in every country so
who actually has to abide by the GDP how
is it basically anyone that's
responsible for EU citizens data
actually anyone who's handling private
data that can be a dentist that can be a
lawyer that can be a simple web shop
where people are providing their name
their shipping address so anyone who is
storing handling private data need to
follow the regulation and I think that
pretty much every businesses it's quite
rare you don't store any private data if
nothing else your employees private data
so if you have employees if you have
customers you most probably and need to
follow the GDP are so as people creating
in maintaining software systems how does
JD PR affect us like as software
engineers in why should we care I think
there are different levels of software
engineering or different type of
companies who should follow what is it
the first level is perpetual license
offer producers the old way you know
that when you crates something you burn
on CD and you sell it but when you do
that you are actually not handling
private information with the software
you are not the one who are providing
the service you're running assume
someone is buying that software and
installing and then running that in that
case you are not touching any private
information
so directly you don't need to follow
gdpr power
your customers will need to follow gdpr
and if your system is not designed in a
way that they can effectively and follow
that they will by someone else in your
software and also if you provide
supports on-site supports you will touch
private data and then you need to follow
this regulation so that at the second
level when you are providing some sort
of high level engineering support or you
are actually selling on project basis
hours development hours and in an
environment where your employees are
actually handling or can touch private
private data this means that you are not
every day exposed to private data but
you need to think through internally and
you need to implement internal policies
that how that person later should enter
to your company for instance if your
software engineer is doing a debugging
and for for for a customer and you get
the database dump or memory dump and for
for that debugging and that might
contain and private data it is okay to
have that that is it is nothing you
should avoid and if you cannot provide a
support you can make so you can regulate
and you can implement policies which you
can depend on each access it's the
private data but once you are you
finished with for instance debugging
then you need to for instance delete the
data or you need to find reasons to keep
that data so that I think is the second
level and the third level where you
expose every day for you know handling
private data that's software service and
e-commerce and when sulfon engineers
forms an integral parts of the data
processing you are not just developing
but here you are maintaining the live
system and that makes basically an
integral parts of the data management
but all this
from the level one is as an importance
it is important to keep in mind that
someone in the process will need to
touch private data yes so usually you
just anonymize any data I'm provided to
you for the bugging anyway wouldn't you
I mean that'd be the best approach and
in am ionization is yes it is it is a it
can be an approach but it just imagine
the use case what I just provided when
you get the database dump and if the
customer says please find a bug and most
businesses are over it and we won't
accept a database from a client and it's
been anonymized first what are the
potential fines if you violate the gdpr
is there any kind of strike or warning
system or will you will your business be
penalized immediately there is there is
a warning and there are actually quite
quite a few countries were Prince's in
Austria where they had implements the
law which says that the first time you
get a warning first from the authorities
and not not a fine but it if you have
negligence and gross negligence or you
are doing really bad things with the
data and a willfulness can be proven
then you may get to find right away okay
but if you make a mistake an honest
mistake then yes there is a warning and
the warning might be also they can and
force you to stop doing something or
change the way how you manage it that's
that's also a sanction that for instance
you are collecting the the names through
when someone is downloading an e-book
and the author is you can say that no
you should not collect the names or the
email addresses for whatever so that you
should not have the newsletter
implemented on your website just
provided a newsletter or the contents of
the newsletter on your website that is a
sanction way because for multiple
reasons companies may need to collect
say once you collect that data and if
you don't follow that advice or that
requirement
you may face with a big fine and the
fine is it can be quite high sir
it can be up to 20 million or 4% of your
global revenue meaning that the group
level revenue so that I spoke with a
subsidiary of a huge global company a
CEO of that's subsidiary and he told me
I mean he has a couple of thousand
employees so that it's not a small
entity its itself but the company the
global companies is a multi-billion
dollar business and four percent can be
more than the entire revenue of that
subsidiary so that just think about it
we could especially if you are working
for a larger entity larger enterprise
how big the fine can be and that's why
you need to look at how to employ and
gdpr and that's why as a software
engineer you need to design a system
which can be compliant with GD P R
because customers will pay an extra for
that for sure
the US government often present there is
a security privacy trade-off with the
Patriot Act for example the government
for example demand access to all data
and USA to supposedly keep us safe
trading privacy for security what are
your thoughts around the so-called
trade-off and here it relates to GD P R
well I am in a broader sense we are a
social social entities as as human
beings so when when we are interacting
with each other we are exposing or
giving up on our privacy for sure so
there is always a trade-off we don't
have want to limit ourselves to to a
room and not not providing any
information about us privacy and and the
GD P R itself is is not about limiting
everything it is about letting the
people know and letting the people
control how their private data is used
there is a metaphor I read on the other
day that basically big US companies
codes and global companies boots go into
your apartments having a key to your
apartments and look around and do
whatever they want GD P R is just a
requirement that they need to knock
before they are doing so so it's yes
there is a trade-off and m GD P R is not
limiting that trade-off you can you can
sell the data to your third party on the
GD P R but you need to let people know
that you are doing and what you are
doing with with their private data
so there's 99 articles of compliance for
the GD P R which points do we need to
focus on what does it be a minimum we
need to understand and do in order to be
compliant I think one of the the most
important parts but actually if you read
the other parts and you will conclude
that's another requirement that's in
your best interest they follow your
article 25 there's a protection by
design and by default this is a privacy
by design but that is privacy as a
concept that when you design a system
you from day one you need to follow the
principles how you will manage the
private data in that system but if if
you are actually read through the the
other articles of Gd P R you will
realize that it's not the requirements
this is in your best interest to follow
it is something like as an engineering
guideline that when you are designing a
big building with apartments in its and
guideline that you need to design a
bathroom and heating the inside because
if you don't design from the day one and
if you're not thinking about bathrooms
just just imagine you build up the in
the building and then later on you need
to modify that building so you have
bathrooms that is you know there's a lot
lot more work so it's much easier to
have it's in mind that here you will
need to have bathrooms in that building
in there were those apartments and that
should be something obvious actually in
the 19th century it was not obvious and
there are many many buildings built
without bathrooms an apartment without
bathrooms
and later when it became a requirement
he needed to modify the entire building
so it's not not a metaphor which is
silly but actually things changed
regulation and requirements of the
people changed and then the existing
systems needs to be trained and that was
it was actually quite expensive thing to
do it's much easier to start from day
one having its in mind that you need to
have it at the end so getting back to
data protection by design or the privacy
by design
there are several fundamental principles
of this the first is being proactive not
reactive and preventive not remedial so
that when when you are designing your
system you try to design in a way to
prevent things rather than then on a
lean way or manage the issues later on
yeah
yeah sure the second is privacy as the
default setting so that when you are
managing private data then you need to
do it in a way that that's a default and
because the full truth if you are having
something else for instance if you have
a data collection and you're exposing
someone to a more excessive data
collection you need to set it up in a
way that's the less of that but there
are ways when you cannot do you on the
complete privacy just think about being
a headhunter and then when someone is
applying a cv to your system you cannot
say that I will not sell that data to
the companies because that's the the
basic nature of your business you are
going to companies as a headhunter and
you are selling private data the
Seavey's to companies but that's the
nature of the business and in that's the
the way how you do UN and that's the
expectation of the customer ok so that
the default setting as a privacy should
reflects your business and your way of
of protecting data for individuals for
instance as a headhunter or a headhunter
website that didn't it
should be protected from anyone else
than the companies you are connecting
with so that just limiting to the basic
one so we're going to move into a
section on our terminology now so what
are the specific roles involved in gdpr
compliance and what are the
responsibilities I noticed that there is
like a control or a process a data
protection officer DPO and in subjects
do you just want to like them to find
what they are sure so the data subject
is a natural person and it's important
when we're talking on private data it is
always connected to a natural person if
it is not then it's not a private data
at that simple it will be extended by a
privacy regulation so the metadata and
even for metadata and not about just
private individuals but just saying at
gdpr of the data subject is the person
who can be identified with that data in
a way in a direct or indirect way and it
is important that identification parts
you know how you can do that but let's
jump so that the second rule is a
controller the controller is the first
entity it's usually a company who is
entering into relationship with the
private individual
for instance the website provider
whatsoever and there are processors and
the subprocessors of the data so that
for instance if if you were running a
website and you are running a webshop
under that's website and and people are
submitting their private sim information
through that and you are running it in
Amazon Amazon is a processor you are as
a controller having liability to your
processor so that if they are doing
something wrong or if they are not
following the rules then you are liable
for that this is a little bit more
complex because the processor has his
own liability as well but your
relationship is regulated through the
DPA they the processing amendments or
agreements and so the controller and the
processor need to sign that and that
processor needs to follow what is set in
that if if the processor tells that I
will resell that data and you sign it
then the professor cannot be liable so
what's the data protection officer data
protection officer is actually one
person or it can be a group so that one
person and the group under reports into
that person its role who's having
certain liabilities and certain
responsibilities to inform the
management's about risks and keep the
data in-house it's something like an
accountant of data basically inside the
organization the European regulation try
to influence that it's you know they the
management is this basic thing as having
an accountant so the role is is
basically it's like close to the CI a--
so role it is a something like
compliance officer so that those are I
think the closest roles under other
jurisdictions there is a software
engineer could I have multiple roles and
if so which would they be the software
engineer as I mentioned I mean search
engine can be a DPO first of all so that
can be in in in a situation because the
DPO the needs are the most important
thing requirements need to understand
how the data is process in that company
and if the software engineer is the
right person to manage that then let's
be it but that DPO needs also follow
regulation so it is good to know the
regulations and combining that knowledge
with that but besides that software
engineer as I mentioned earlier there
are I think the three levels I'm I
mentioned how they touch the personal
data one is a software engineer so the
woman the perpetual Isis software
the second is a software engineer as a
provider of high level supports or you
know working on a project or for a
customer so you are touching someone
else's data and the third when you are a
software is a service provider or
e-commerce and I think those those
levels when you are working as a
software engineer for companies those
are the levels when you need to think
what is the risk and what
for private data because the more you
were exposed the more you need to worry
about that and the more you need to know
about it yeah so what's the easiest way
for software engineers to actually know
what they need to be considering rather
than waiting the 99 had a course I think
circling back to the privacy by design I
think there should be when you were
architecting the system and you need to
think about the privacy of the
individuals when when you are for
instance having an entity relation
diagram you need to ask yourself ok what
is the risk and is it a private data and
if it's a private data then you need to
set the level of the risk for that
private data what I would suggest and
there are multiple ways to look at that
but what I would suggest is having a
four level risk level implementing a
risk level for a private data so not
every private data boring to be the same
risk if it's expose or go to the public
process in a sexual orientation it's not
the same risk as for instance IP address
or our cookie on your website if you
lose that data if there is a breach and
that goes out to the public you may face
higher fines if you're publishing the
sexual orientation of someone for
instance so what I would suggest is
categorizing and the categorization is a
following and the number one is
sensitive private data and sensitive
private data is actually defined in GDP
are there are racial or ethnic origin
political opinions religious or
philosophical beliefs trade union
membership and processing of genetic
data biometric data data concerning
health and either concerning a natural
person's sex life or sexual orientation
that is the sensitive that's the
category of the sensitive data if you
manage that you need to take a deep
breath and later on take it quite
seriously because if if you don't have a
good reason
so you handle that information you
better not to men
yeah then the the second level I would
say is the data where individuals can be
identified with just that information
for instance first name last name
birthdate
that's tupple is something you can use
to identify someone without any other
system so just looking at this
information identifies the person the
third level would be for instance
something that it doesn't identify right
away but with looking at the system that
topo and it's not the record that Topol
doesn't identify you right away but it
takes for someone or another software
engineer or well-educated professional
to identify it with just a little work
and for instance phone number if you are
not a telco provider phone number can be
something like that
in multiple systems if for instance if
you're not having phone numbers or
connecting phone numbers to names just
having phone numbers naked that itself
doesn't identify in your system a
private individual but you could look it
up in a lot of databases it can take
just a few google search to find the
person yeah and the fourth level is
something which requires more work and
connecting databases which may not be
public but that can be used with a
little bit more work someone can
identify you
I would princess most of the cases I
would put IP address in that category
but again it really depends on how you
are running your system what you were
anything but IP address if you are just
logging IP address of website visitor
and you're never never connecting it to
a private individuals name it would take
a lot of work for you to connect it to
someone someone else but it's it's
possible yeah yeah so once you you have
that categorization and there is a the
fifth category it's not private data so
for instance log of a system or if
you're working for manufacturing the
difference
lock in that system is not considered
private data at all so when you looking
at the entity relation diagram you just
mark these which data considered to be
private and what is level of the risk
and once you you have that then you
start thinking of the I would suggest
the following framework the first
thinking why you were collecting that
data what is the reason it is important
from any perspective because once you
document that reason you can go to an
attorney and consult with that just
write it down as a professional but you
don't need to overthink you don't need
to use the legal language this simple
documentation what is the reason you are
collecting metadata princess in a CRM
system
you know storing information can be for
legal purposes as well you know that I
received an order you know send me this
package and so on and the reason why you
are storing because if there is a
disputes you need to prove that an
employee of your customer has ordered
something or it can be for instance if
for invoices invoices have private data
as itself but the authorities require
you to store that so what is the reason
why you are doing that and document that
yeah and it can be a business reason as
well and now we are not talking about
documentation which might be Gd pair
compliant but the work you need to do
before you go to and that's only then
the second is think about how the data
will be deleted can you delete that data
and if you don't know when the data will
be deleted
better not to collect it and better cut
it out because if the data after for
instance termination of relationship
with a customer needs to be deleted
unless you have a reason to keep that
but you still need to have a deadline
for deleting that again the invoice is a
perfect example even if the customer
tells you delete everything
and gdpr tells you in that case you need
to deliver everything except you have
the right and you have the reason to
keep that so that you need the documents
why you are keeping it in voices because
effects author it is I mean it is that
simple so if you have documents it then
it's also how that data will be used
later on and so on but if you have that
in your hand
at least documented the reasons when you
will and the lifecycle as well then you
can go to an attorney and then the
attorney will able to provide you advice
and based on based on that situation
what today and how to write a privacy
policy for instance which covers your
way of of managing data because in a lot
of cases as mention gdpr
is just about letting the people know
what you are doing and if you are doing
something which is undocumented it is
not included in your privacy policy then
it's it's illegal but maybe if you just
included in your privacy policy then it
can be good sometimes it is not that
easy sometimes you cannot collect data
by just including the information
because if you for instance you don't
have the read and you cannot underpin
what is the reasons to collect that
information then gdpr tells that
actually data stacking or collecting
data because just because we don't know
what we will do in the in the future
that is that is something you cannot do
even though that you write it down in
your privacy policy ever thought about a
master's degree to advance your career
as a software developer the UC Irvine
16-month professionally oriented master
of software engineering program is made
for you taught by experts in the field
the program combines hands-on
experiences and fundamentals and latest
trends with professional development for
successful careers after graduation
hurry applications for fall 2019 are due
December 15th
MSE ICS UCI dot edu to learn more and
start your application today so just on
the unpack apps so what if a user wants
the data purged or modified does the
business have to purge or modify all
copies and backups including offsite the
basic or the simple answer yes the more
complex answer is it depends it depends
because just think about it what is the
reason of the backup the reason of the
backup is if something goes wrong it's
not the redundancy it is you have most
probably you implement redundancy in
your life system raid Ltd's multiple
servers copying and shadow copies of
your online system that's not for faults
in your system it is more like someone
hits delete accidentally and delete
everything in your live system then it's
better to have a backup and if you are
for instance managing the data for some
medical data for a hospital or you are a
bank and you're managing the people's
money if the data is deleted that will
have a serious consequences for the
business and for your customers as well
so the backup is a weight a multiple
ways to protects the private individuals
as well and their interest as well too
you have to have a backup since all the
requirements are not that prescriptive
what we're supposed to be doing with
backups yes because we were thinking
with our GDP our lawyer that for
instance if you take back the tape drive
the only tape drive for you know purging
private data that simple records that
might damage the backup itself so what
you are doing is actually risking in
case of an emergency
to get back to the normal level yeah but
the simple rule is you need to purge the
records from your backups as well the
more complex is thinking through yeah if
you think that there is a good reason
and you can by consulting with your
attorney there is a good reason and you
can find a legal
ace storing a backup and not deleting
from the backup then there might be a
way not to do that and you say that okay
I'm I'm just keeping it in a bunker
close down and there is a process that I
implements a Chinese wall that my online
system cannot get to the backup because
it it is stored so far higher another
company and when we are restoring there
needs to be two people who is there and
is recovering the encryption key of the
backup incidents and so new implements
in a way that the data cannot be used
for anything else then just for the
backup and you set the rights dates that
okay
I'm keeping the backup for one year
whatever then you can say that okay I
don't delete it because the risk of for
instance destroying the backup or
damaging the backup is higher than the
risk of someone's data is in in the
backup so the entity holding the
subjects data must be able to erase all
the data of the subject so I add the
subjects request right yep so I'm that's
like the subject has the right to be
forgotten but what sort of things do we
need to do to make this possible again
it starts from the design or how you are
hitting the system and it's why when you
are a software developer who's not
running a system but you're developing a
software which is used by people who are
managing private data it's better to
keep it in mind because your customers
will denounce a way of deleting private
data they will have a headache and if
you can provide a cure for that headache
that's that's good business so if you
cannot are hit Act because it's a legacy
system and most of the system right now
is like a citizen we will not throw them
away and will not start scratching so if
you need to design bathrooms in a
building where it was not prepared for
in that case what I would do is start
with a wide wards and drawing with a
green and the red pencil or marker on
that and draw a big rectangle saying we
delete everything that's with red and
starts drawing things you need to keep
you know that what is the part of the
system you need to keep for instance
invoices invoices need to be kept for
five seven years depending on the
jurisdiction you are in after a
determination of the relationship with
your customer then it is something you
need to delete in a different way and
then you ask okay you need to keep logs
because of trope prevention okay there
is a reason why you can keep that many
logs for a longer period then you draw a
little rectangle saying that okay locks
can be kept for another year and so on
and so on and then you starts when you
have these green rectangles on the
charts you have a large sets of data you
want to keep or you should keep as an
obligation but then you continue with
the red and saying that okay now what
can I delete from the green ones in
order to minimize the impacts versus in
the logs you can delete the IP address
or just the last octet of the IP
addresses and saying that okay that
something cannot be used for identifying
a person but at least I know where that
was coming from so the subject has the
right to access and extract and modify
their own personal data with gdpr right
so what do we need to do in order to
make this possible
first I think when you design a delete a
system or how you delete the private
data that system also needs able to list
on the data so it create a dump about
the user and once you have the dump you
need to be able to present that
information to your customer by
individual so that in facebook for
instance if you go to your accounts you
can export every data Facebook stores
about you I mean they say it contains
every data but it's a hell lot of data
and a lot of details what you can do and
you need to be able to do the same the
other changing and right - if something
for instance your name has been recorded
with a typo or something else it's
towards about you in the wrong way the
person needs to be able to
ask for change and you need to have the
the process to do so it doesn't mean
that you need to have you know on online
a system and a website where customers
can change every day that but your for
instance a support personnel or someone
needs to be able to change that data
later on so that there needs to be
implemented a way to do that moving into
a planning and implementation section
when GDP I was brought into law we saw a
number of our websites like the Los
Angeles Times do things like Ben bu from
viewing their website well they figured
out what to do that is a sort of
strategy work mini au citizens live in
non-eu countries does this really mean
yeah I I don't know I mean I don't think
it's the right way there are many other
companies for instance Twilio they the
implemented GDP our own way that
everyone got the GDP our compliance
serviced so that globally because they
said it's easier to implement as a
global company GDP are in their entire
company then you know just separates for
you and only you
citizens and it's trillions is usually
not a direct relationship with the
private individuals they are processor
most of the cases but they design the
system for everyone to comply with GDP
are and that is something which points
out that GDP are can be a global
standard and yes Los Angeles Times maybe
have the ability to ban but it's also a
bad message to people living in the u.s.
or living someone else's they cannot
follow simple regulation to disclose how
the private data is managed on the
website I think that as we go on that
will be a stigma and and stigmatizing
that you are not respecting the people's
privacy it's not not a good message do
you know of any specific frameworks or
tools that make it easier to me GDP our
requirements for software engineers
unfortunately I don't have something
which could be considered as silver
bullets
especially that many many ways of many
Thada what I would princess sir I said
an unusual tool is a data catalog there
are multiple data catalogues where you
can documents it's more like an entity
diagram or meta and to the diagram so
it's a meta database containing the
private data what you are having where
you are storing that and you can
documents where you are storing so what
I mentioned the documentation inside
your system that can make your life
easier but that feeling in that database
at that data catalog you can have
scripts you can have a lot of things who
is that process but at the end you are
the one as a software engineer who will
design the system and you will be the
one who knows how data is handled in in
that it's something like is there a tool
for writing a software from the
customers fineman's yes there are some
and you know Ultimates I sought for
developments and but most of the cases
it's better to you know do it in an old
way and go through the development
process so there are other tools like AI
tools which can help you identifying
personal data inside your database
giving you a holistic view especially
for legacy systems they need to think
through how that private data and in you
need to sit down at two documents how
the private data flows into that system
so that AI tools can scan to point out
the risk that okay these records have or
these tuples might be viewed as a
personal later so what are some of these
tools
for instance asier has data catalog
Microsoft Azure and there is a way to
have that documentation in place and
importing but it's it's not a again
silver bullets slightly more
sophisticated way of documentation than
having a spreadsheet but so we've talked
about architectural decisions what about
coding testing logging monitoring what
parts of these activities do we need to
modify and how do we need to modify them
to satisfy gdpr compliance I think one
principle I would say that centralize
your your
was centralized a private data in
one-one database or as few databases as
possible I mean when you design the
database on relational database it's
it's a usual way of thinking that okay
will you minimize and you only have one
place where the data is stored
but for performance or other reasons you
may have copies of personal data in
multiple other systems so what I would
suggest that for instance you have the
private name first name last name
address even the IP address if you are
connecting that credit card whatsoever
in one central place and you only use
foreign keys in the other systems so in
a way that you are anonymizing in other
parts of the system in the private data
you are using random tokens instead of
the private data which will slow down
the system
in fact because a join is something
which takes time in a system but that at
the ends when it comes to deleting the
data you need to delete it from that
central database and then that's foreign
key can be in your system forever
yes I mean often you'll have quite a few
different parts of an organization like
you'll have marketing research customer
relations support how do we design for
tracking all the data stores of the
organization across all of those areas
like say for an example you may have a
user that's got parts of their identity
in each one of those years of your
organization and they're all in
different data stores and there's a
really no easy way that you can pull
them all together and centralize them so
how do you actually track them across
all of those areas it is very very
complex what I would suggest and it's
the first step I mean first step is just
think through how the data flows before
you do anything so that just have a data
map where the data flows and that data
map is basically when you sit down with
different heads of this areas and your
documents where the data should go and
accidentally can come up that that is
more documentation talking meetings so
on but then obviously you will make
mistakes people will forget about oh
yeah
we are using that reports from time to
time we are exporting to CSV and then
doing marketing doing a little bit
transformation here and there and then I
forget to delete that CSV on my laptop
and blah blah blah so what I recommend
so after you have this a data flow you
documents how the data goes inside your
organization and what are the reasons
it's still not the compliant C so you
haven't checked with attorney whether
it's good or not but at least you know
you are in control then the seconds you
owed it that documentation the auditing
can be multiple ways one way which is
quite effective way is it's a metaphor
for anger graphic so anger graph is
using medical imaging and when you are
putting some special liquid into Wiens
and then and you see how that special
liquid goes through your body when you
are in an MRI okay you need to do
something similar princess you drop fake
information into the website sign ups
and then scan all your laptops your
employees laptops for that private
information and then you will find out
that oh that information is you know
that marketing is exporting the CSV and
from time to time to from this system
and they'll forget to delete or we
forgets that we have another software
service system for customer support
because customer support may have you
know multiple systems they are using and
so on insulin so but if you cannot
inject Francis fake information into
your system you can just select random
ones and search in your system for that
and search the databases for that
information just through the dumps you
dump the entire information and then you
can see okay is that records documents
it is it something we are knowing about
so that the first step is really
identifying the way how information
spread across your organization that is
the single most important part of that
and I can tell something it won't be
holistic and were you you will not
100% ever for sure so you need to stop
it at one point and say okay this is
what I think covers most of the ways how
we are managing private information this
is where it spreads I know there are
ways but let's start doing risk analysis
based on that because you can do this
forever and then you look at you know
what are the risks what happens with
that CS reason on your system and when
you do this risk analysis you were
actually doing something which is
required by a GDP are basically so that
this process needs to be documented as
well so when when you are doing that
okay laptops are having encryption and
login and screen lock and so on and so
on and so on so I consider this a medium
risk for that or low risk or whatsoever
so you document that thing and then you
are doing a risk mitigation so if you
find that okay maybe we should turn on
for instance encryption on the laptops
where private information is stored disk
encryption or maybe we should rather not
have you know exporting CSV and or Excel
we should rather have an online
interface for the marketing where they
don't export but they can use from the
browser and manage the data from the
browser so so the data is not exported
and so on and so so you do some risk
mitigation and use some steps obviously
you will not able to mitigate all the
risks but you need to start from the
from the top what are the top risk you
identified any documents the reason okay
this is what I have time for doing this
is what I will do and this is the old
way a minute if you have implemented ISO
27001 this is quite similar if you have
done HIPAA or something else quite
similar but this is called privacy
impact assessment and if you are
managing a lot of private data you need
to do so you're obliged to do that
privacy impact assessment but if you are
not obliged because of your size of your
nature I would still recommend doing it
because this is who
it's good way of looking at your system
your organization how how they are
managing data what happens when an
employee decides to deploy a rogue trial
or test system using personal
identifiable information whether
accessible externally or just internally
does this create millions of dollars of
a liability for the organization well if
it's an accidental thing you may face
libel is in especially if you didn't do
privacy impact assessments and you
haven't identified risks and and you
didn't do anything to mitigate the risks
so there are were obvious low-hanging
fruits how you could prevent that
accidental leakage then for sure you are
liable so how do you stop your employees
doing things that you don't know about
other they're going to expose you like
that there is I think the - two things
one the system your system need to be
able to manage people and accidents the
second is a various and never ness
training so you need to educate your
employees about the way how they need to
manage the private data and if if you
didn't do anything about it then then
you may face with serious consequences
but if you did and still happens you you
may that can be this is hard to judge
and this something you need to consult
with an attorney case-by-case but if you
did the privacy impact assessments you
are seriously doing the improvements on
and on and and you are doing a very nice
trainings and still happens a data
breach by your employee then then the
third thing if that happens you need to
act and there are certain requirements
how how you need to manage a data breach
you need to for instance let the
authorities know in 72 hours
so that there are requirements in gdpr
that's the process have you managed and
the data breach and if you manage the
data breach in a professional way that
can seriously
lower the the consequences it can be
just a warning at the end not to fine
you've got a warning okay units
to implement and and you already know
that I am and we need to do something
about it you need to improve your
processes but but there are things and
the gdpr is not something it tells that
okay you you cannot make mistakes at all
you need to make steps in order to
minimize those risks the head is I'm
defending against the employee doing
this differ from any outsider doing
something similar
privates impact assessments and look at
that is it really necessary for instance
that I'm pointing having access to that
data or is it the way how that employee
should have access their differences
supports should supports able to get
access by typing in anyone's email
address get access to the data so that
the person
I mean if most of the people would say
yeah but what if you implements at
supports simple questions that please
tell the last four digit of credit card
or please say your name and birthday the
whatsoever so some some identification
process for the customer which works
through the phone through the email or
whatsoever a newer system does not allow
of the personnel to get access to that
information unless that authentication
is done so that process support agent
need to type in the last four digits of
the credit card number and then the
system allows you to enter so you need
to design in a way that people cannot
make mistakes and the risks are
minimized by the system and also the
people need to be trained and and tell
them the stories what happened and learn
from if something a breach happens or
close to something a breach then it
needs to be communicated how that's
should have been handled there was a
customer who came to us and hand all
stare about cancelling someone's
accounts claiming that was his accounts
and deleting all the data and it came to
actually to the data privacy officer the
DPO and were privacy
that they came to ask how could they
hand over the data and how could they
manage it because the system stopped
them to do that but if the customer was
saying that they will sue us if we don't
do this and that and it turned out that
the customer was not identified in the
right way it was an unauthorized or
unauthenticated channel when or how they
communicates it so that they couldn't
make sure that the customer was the one
they're talking to luckily they didn't
hand over any information because they
were trained but they were thinking and
they were they had have started doing it
but the system stopped them so that sort
of social engineering could have words
on them if the system doesn't stop them
even though that the training and even
though the Avernus what we try to raise
in or support personnel later on it
turned out that wasn't I mean that was
in the social engineering at all just
simply that was the customer and that
was the customer claim just didn't have
the way to old indicates himself so it
turned out good
but still we noted as a breach or close
to a breach because the supports people
wanted to over ride the system and then
then we use this an example to tell that
what what could have go wrong in that
one case yes we're gonna have to start
wrapping up this one just in conclusion
do you know have any good privacy
awareness and training resources what I
would suggest is read through the gdpr
summaries there are many many summaries
of the articles but at least read
through the in the ninety nine article
titles
so they start with the source I think it
is important understanding the
principles in in the GDP are in the
importance you understand what are the
topics you need to think about first and
they're the very masses is a tricky
thing you need to sometimes you need to
go quite deep inside you're in that
territory if you're working with for
instance healthcare data that's it's a
quite special
territory as I mentioned
sensitive private information that is a
completely different way than for
instance managing ecommerce private data
so I think there are many goods channels
at Treasury comm we also publish some
materials and and videos about s-- about
that's what we recorded on previous
shows I've got a bunch of those in the
show notes as I thanks for joining us
today yes fern thank you for having me
for suffering engineering radio this was
kim cotta digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/sc radio thanks for listening to se
Radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC radio
slack calm you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening